hey everyone thanks for listening to the
grow your life podcast my name is jared
mikowski and if we haven't met yet i
help coaches trainers mentors authors
speakers scale their business build
their brand and make more money using
the internet to do so now today i have a
guest becky sikanovi she is a functional
nutritionist who works with professional
men and women who want to optimize their
bodies and become their best selves who
also lose weight not as maybe the main
goal but as a side effect of working
with her so welcome to the podcast today
becky thank you thank you so much for
having me
so tell me a little bit about how you
got into this and and how long you've
been doing this and and we particularly
we have a number of people that listen
to the podcast that might even be doing
what you're doing and they want to glean
from and learn from your journey oh yeah
and honestly functional nutrition is a
really expanding um field in the
industry and more than ever we need more
people to kind of take their training to
the next level and understand what it
means to practice functional nutrition
as opposed to just you know slashing
people's calories right and left
increasing their activity and then
scratching their heads and you know
wondering why nothing is working for
people um so we really would love to see
more people work on optimizing the body
and losing weight as a side effect so if
anyone's interested this is definitely
the route that you want to go because
it's not only you're going to get a
better client result but your clients
are going to be thrilled with the result
that they get to
yeah
how do you how did you start doing that
so
so we'll go backwards and i went to
messiah college and
graduated you know with a degree in
exercise physiology you know and all
that great stuff
and i started out as a personal trainer
in the gym you know kind of like doing
what everybody else did and you know i
would write these great workout programs
for my clients and you know give them
very sensible
you know plans to follow and i started
to notice that in some cases it would
work really great at first and then it
would stop working or
in like the case of adults that were in
like 30s 40s 50s it wouldn't work at all
and i was scratching my head thinking
you know what am i doing wrong what
could i what could i be doing better you
know maybe the client's not even being
honest with me you know and things like
that and i realized that there was a lot
more to it than just cutting calories
out of somebody's daily intake and you
know having them do more exercise there
you can't treat the body like a human
calculator you really have to treat it
like a complex organism which it is
so
that at that point i started scratching
my head going okay why are why are my
best results with people in their 20s
and not so much people in their 30s 40s
50s and so on because at that point
their bodies had started to
create metabolic adaptation they had you
know maybe not the best digestion their
hormones had started to imbalance um and
their stress levels had gone up and
accumulated you know when you're 20
everything's great you know you've got
great hormones you have little stress
you know it's really easy to get a great
result but as you get older and exposed
to all of these things
it becomes a little bit more complicated
so
uh i i started to realize this now at
the same time
i also started to have some
kind of peculiar issues and i started to
notice some things were not quite right
and i went to see my doctor so i i'd had
like hives and of course the doctor sent
me to a food you know allergist had some
tests run
i was on zyrtec multiple times a day and
then that where there were more symptoms
that arose from that so they wanted to
refer me to a rheumatoid you know
someone that treats rheumatoid arthritis
and i was like i don't have that i don't
need to go to a rheumatologist and then
i was so upset you know in the course of
one of these appointments i started
getting heart palpitations and they're
like well we don't do that you need to
go to a cardiologist now and i'm like
this all started with hives
you know like this is just bizarre so i
gave up on that route and was like i'm
i'm really done with everything that
medicine has to offer because this is
just creating more issues for me and i
don't feel any better
so i was working with my chiropractor
one day
and he ran a device over my body that
measured inflammation
and he said uh wow your inflammation is
off the charts i need to refer you to my
mother-in-law who practices naturopath
medicine you know she's a naturopath at
this point i'm like i will do anything i
am so tired of you know
not getting anywhere and at this point
um
i had lost a lot of weight so i was in
like little girl size you know size 16
pants which is like kind of concerning
my body wasn't holding on to weight i
was weight training i was eating protein
you know all of that stuff so there was
something really wrong
uh and i went to see her and she
completely opened my eyes to how the
body is more of a complex organism that
you need to treat as a whole instead of
trying to section off different systems
and trying to work with each system
independent because they really don't
work that way they were don't work
independently of each other they all
work together
so we did a heavy metal cleanse
uh she fixed my gut i had gut issues for
a long time um i had been put on
menocycline continuously while i was in
high school for uh acne issues and being
on an antibiotic continuous really
wrecks your gut i didn't know any better
you know and as it turned out my my um
and if you look at my skin now you would
never guess but you know if you um
have like a food intolerance that you
don't know about which i did it can show
up on the skin so i cut out dairy i cut
out gluten and lo and behold my skin had
you know healed up and i'm thinking
this was so easy well you know
relatively speaking this is so much more
logical than the other approach
and i was put through the wringer only
to be put on more medications and things
weren't working and things started to
escalate and i forgot to add uh that at
one point i was showing signs of
estrogen dominance and um i knew there
was an issue because i i
had so much breast sensitivity that if
somebody sat down on the couch next to
me too hard i'd be in extreme pain
i'm like this is not normal so i went to
an endocrinologist i had labs run they
were so unimpressed by my labs they
didn't even call me with a result i had
to call them and ask hey what was the
outcome of my labs
didn't call me there was nothing you
know so
all of these things together you know
like i said
led me to this naturopath doctor i
worked with her and she mentored me for
12 years
and throughout the course of this whole
journey i said you know what i do not
want anybody else to ever have to go
through this you know i want to make it
my my mission in life to make sure that
clients that i work with from now on
never have to go through any of this i
want to make sure that i can help them
pinpoint these root causes and maximize
their life you know and not just keep
throwing band-aids at things whether
it's you know more cardio less calories
you know just take this random probiotic
doesn't really it doesn't really get at
the root cause of things so fast forward
and i was mentored by a functional
medicine doctor for two years after that
which really expanded my you know my
knowledge and understanding of things
and recently um i've been working with
the kalish institute which is a
functional medicine online university
and just continuing to increase my
knowledge base you know and things like
that because we're what we're really
seeing coming out of this this pandemic
is that more people than ever are
dealing with some degree of adrenal
fatigue which a lot of medical
professionals don't like that term but
unfortunately it has the greatest
um
you know greatest word recognition
amongst most people they know what that
means
so essentially people's stress systems
have been pushed too far
and they're not able to get through the
day they're exhausted they're tired they
go to their doctor their doctor puts
them on an antidepressant which doesn't
really do them any good or an
anti-anxiety they get worse and as it
turns out they're just suffering from
deficiencies they're suffering from you
know nutritional deficiencies um
they've been under a prolonged stress
response so their body starts to break
down and we're going to be seeing this
in epidemic levels if we haven't already
so it's really important to circle back
all the way to the beginning when i said
we need more people that are into
functional nutrition we need a whole
army of people that understand how to
help people and not just try to program
them like a calculator eat less of this
eat more of this eat more protein eat
more veggies those things are good but
it's just scratching the surface and
it's not really getting to
some of the deeper layers of what it
means to you know nourish and
um you know kind of care for our bodies
let me let me ask you while you're
working with people
um what do you see is is one of the
biggest things that
that
you find is a roadblock that
you've learned to break through with
people to help bring them results when
they feel stuck that's a great question
they can't break through
that's a really great question i'm gonna
answer it from two perspectives so i'm
going to answer from the body
perspective and i'm going to answer from
the mind perspective
so from the body perspective the number
one thing that i see holding people back
is their digestive health number one so
either i would say like 90 of the people
that i work with have uh constipation
and they have bloating and they've been
taught that it's normal for these things
to happen and you should just drink
miralax and everything's fine or you
know maybe you take it up a level and
you're diagnosed with ibs and that's
still not really much help because that
doesn't really mean anything it just
means there's an issue but we haven't
identified do you have a probiotic or do
you need probiotics do you have a
bacterial imbalance you know do you lack
digestive enzymes you know all of those
things so the the gut bacteria is so
valuable and such a cornerstone to
weight loss that the medical community
has started
doing processes called fecal transplants
so a fecal transplant is just like what
it sounds like so they will take the
stool from a lean individual and they
will transfer it to an obese individual
because the bacteria in the lean
individual's gut is so valuable and so
highly functional keeping this person at
this optimal weight that they will
transfer it to an obese individual with
really great results and that's how
important the gut bacteria is if your
gut bacteria is off maybe you've been on
multiple courses of antibiotics you've
got the diet dialed in you've got the
exercise dialed in if your bacteria is
off
you're not going to be burning
carbohydrates efficiently you're going
to start storing things you're going to
have an inflammatory response which is
like way above what most people assume
most people think oh i should just get
my thyroid tested and be put on
medication
that never works in my experience right
ever i mean it's it's great to get that
sort of thing checked out but most
people assume once they're put on a
thyroid medication they're just going to
start automatically losing weight and i
found that that's very rarely the case
so i would say to answer your question
that's the first
you know um
major roadblock that you know i help
people overcome so they can start losing
weight the other
answer portion or um part to your
question is the mental emotional and i
would say the the type of people that i
tend to work with have a real
difficult time prioritizing themselves
and tend to be
self-sacrificial to the point where
they sacrifice
their own goals in order to
serve their family serve their business
serve their job any of those things and
they just take whatever the leftover
scraps are and put it themselves and
then instead of a process taking three
months it can take 16 months or it can
take 24 months because they give give
and there's nothing left for themselves
so a large part of my coaching involves
helping people recognize some of these
behaviors and giving them steps to you
know start to make changes like
realizing that they're worth it
realizing that they have people that are
codependent on them and helping them get
out of that
yeah
how how would you
help somebody
with that because there's there's
obviously a lot of guilt and even shame
involved around that especially feeling
like
if i'm no longer codependent with
somebody that now that makes me a bad
person
right i'm actually hurting them or that
i'm helping them
how do you walk somebody through that
that's a really great question so
another part of the um coaching training
i've had is i'm a trauma-informed coach
so basically what that means is i've
taken certification courses through my
church
uh about trauma and things like that so
i have a a pretty good understanding of
where a lot of these mechanisms are
coming from
so and of course i have to add you know
disclaimer if you feel like you need
therapy please do not only speaking
therapy you know that's that should be
your first stop but uh you know in
individuals that are having difficulty
prioritizing themselves and like you
said feeling the guilt and the shame of
being self-sacrificial usually what they
what i do is i lead them through an
exercise and i say well what does it
look like if you're not available to
take care of your family what is it what
does it look like
if you are you know this many years down
the road you can't play with your
children you can't play with your
grandchildren you know things like that
but then what does it look like when
you're healthy how many more things can
you do with them you know what what does
your future look like now and give them
the choice i don't force anybody to do
anything i just say this is totally up
to you and you're yeah your hand is on
the throttle and you can control how
fast this process moves but i just want
you to think about those things yeah
typically when i work with mothers that
are extremely self-sacrificial for their
family i just explained to them my
favorite analogy
you have to put on your own oxygen mask
before you put on anyone else's oxygen
mask like when you're in an airplane the
nest drop down you have to put your own
on first before you can help anybody
else and usually when i explain it to
people that way then the gears start
turning and they start to realize
they need to start making different
choices and here's where i would love to
like
dive deeper into that right there let's
say that you have a mom or a dad
who
they okay
they need to take care of their own
oxygen mask but they also want to take
care of their family but they just don't
even have the energy to do that they
feel like they have too much going on
to even
do that
sure can't even
take five minutes
to not do that i i just had um
you know i actually had two people in
the last week
um
tell me that you know i'm just i'm too
overwhelmed
by
the idea of even building a business i
think i'm gonna give up and just go back
and work the corporate job oh okay and
so they're just they're overwhelmed by
taking care of themselves and their
family and they're like
they can't
do it
all and they're then beating themselves
up even
about it
feeling guilt and shame
and they're struggling
to
they end up in a cycle right back where
they started
right absolutely and and it is cyclical
you know where it just goes around it
around around the the guilt and shame
cycle repeats and there's no lower
vibrating emotion than guilt and shame
there's nothing i mean it's been you
know they measure it you know joy and
love is all the way up here and guilt
and shame is all the way down here so
the more that your body is resonating at
guilt and shame the more the disease
processes can start to take over the
sicker that you get the lower your
energy you know things like that so in
situations like that i really find that
first of all
the person usually has difficulty
setting boundaries but from a very good
place in their heart if that makes sense
so they have such a desire to serve
others and take care of others and
whatever that their own boundaries kind
of take like you know a back seat and
they have a really hard time setting new
boundaries because they feel like
they're betraying their family somehow
or some other obligation they've
committed themselves to but the reality
is if they're going to break that cycle
they have to create new boundaries
slowly they don't have to be extreme you
know like all of a sudden like all right
i'm not making dinner for anybody this
week figure it out you know
um you know maybe you compromise and
maybe you say okay i'm going to um make
dinner and i'm going to delegate and i'm
going to place an order through
instacart pick it up i'm not going to
shout myself
i'm going to cook dinner you're going to
clean it up and you're going to take
care of the leftovers instead of feeling
like i need to go shopping i need to
cook the dinner i need to pick it up i
need to now take the kids to practice or
whatever else and and to that person
that's in the middle of that situation
they truly don't have the time because
that's what they've created but at the
same time
they can create something that looks
totally different and by no means are
they not you know taking the best care
of their family at that point they've
just learned how to delegate they've
learned how to share jobs they've you
know they've really taught their kids
how to
run a household at that point and i
explained this to a lady not long ago so
she has polycystic ovarian syndrome
which is triggered by stress by the way
and one of the things that i told her
that really hit home and she homeschools
and so on really great person very
kind-hearted lady i said here's the
thing
how many kids do you have
tells me she has eight i said okay
do you want all eight of your children
to watch what you're doing and model the
same process especially your daughters
and she said oh my gosh no i don't and i
said okay
just think about that you know do you
want your daughters feeling exactly how
you feel now and heaven forbid also
having polycystic ovarian syndrome so
not only that once people realize
they're modeling for their kids what
their future selves could look like that
sometimes is enough
you know kindling to start the process
of sparking new thoughts and you know
new processes and like oh wow this is
why this is important it's not just
about me anymore it's how i'm impacting
future generations
maybe i'm setting my own kids up for
failure at this point and then people
start to reevaluate
now now what if you have somebody who
they're in their home and their
they're they're dealing with this
they're setting boundaries and they get
a lot of backlash or they get oh yeah
they get their their kids get angry or
their spouse gets angry that now they're
not doing this and even threatening them
oh sure then they end up right back into
that cycle like what would you say in
that situation that's a really great
question so so the first thing about
that is well first of all anytime that
you set a boundary there's a quote about
this somewhere which i'm probably going
to butcher but anytime that you set a
boundary the people that were taking the
greatest advantage of you because you
had no boundary suddenly is going to
become the most angry because
their you know their cash cow has
suddenly pulled back and is like i'm not
doing this anymore
um so you need number one you need to
expect pushback from those types of
people um and hold your ground and stick
to your guns however
the process does require a little bit of
finesse so if you like i said suddenly
announce you're not making dinner
anymore for anybody and you're not
grocery shopping and you're not doing
anybody's laundry for your own health
they're going to be like what so of
course you're going to get a massive
rebellion but if you take smaller steps
and you sit the family down and you say
listen i need we're going like as a
family we're going to make these changes
because it's important for all of us
especially my health but you know all of
you
this is what the changes are going to
look like and maybe you could you know
if you're in a situation where they
could give you feedback you know
sometimes you can sometimes you can't
sometimes
the the person's you know version of
feedback is just manipulation to keep
you where you're at yeah um but you just
sit them down and just be like this is
what it's going to look like so um you
know if you've got kids that are 16 that
can drive okay listen i'm not grocery
shopping anymore i'm gonna place an
instacart you're gonna pick it up and
put the groceries away a 16 year old can
handle that you know things like that um
yeah so i think it's important to kind
of figure out what your boundaries are
and then start to delegate yeah delegate
and and lay out a long-term plan of
where you eventually want to be instead
of being like all right i'm done
you know
even though that's probably what your
body and your mind needs to make the
transition easier you need to go slower
and just stay hey very good we're going
to be doing love that just go slower do
what you can do
i tell people that often
they they they are like i'm overwhelmed
by all the stuff i have to do to make my
business work i'm overwhelmed i was
about to make my life work and i'm like
just do what you can do
and yet i often hear i say that to
people and their response back is well
i don't feel satisfied with what i can
do and i'm not happy with it
and and
there's these these messages
that people deal with and struggle with
that ultimately again i think goes back
to trauma sure i think goes back to fear
and worry and how we were raised and
that if you don't perform you're not
good enough this performance anxiety
um
i've struggled with that myself
i struggle with that completely that if
i don't do everything as i should quote
unquote according to what
people say i should do that i'm
bad and i have to remind myself that
that's that's not true they're like i
get to create my life
we get to design our lives
absolutely i mean and i think that
that's very common herd mentality is a
species if i don't you know conform to
what the herd expects or wants then i'm
going to be ostracized and i don't get
access to resources and whatever it's
very primal thinking you know when you
feel that your very existence is
threatened because you're not conforming
but the reality is that you know we're
in modern society now and that's not a
concern
you know we still have access to
resources and you know what's what's
really interesting is um
i think in a lot of cases women have
been kind of like passed down this
ancestral belief that they have to trade
their autonomy for protection or
for resource because honestly you go
back multiple centuries that was the
case women were trading their autonomy
for resources for safety for protection
and it's programmed i mean we've seen um
multiple studies on holocaust survivors
like the offspring of holocaust
survivors
and these um
offspring can be clinically diagnosed
with ptsd not because they've you know
gone through any sort of trauma
themselves but because the trauma from
their grandparents or their parents has
been encoded in the dna and been passed
down
and that's not an isolated example i
mean you look at any family and more
more likely than not there's some type
of ancestral trauma that's been passed
down
in some way so it's it's fascinating we
could do a whole podcast on that
actually but it doesn't mean it's a
death sentence it just means that you
know you're resisting some programming
that came was passed down genetically
and you just work on slowly
reprogramming but also acknowledging
like this and this part's important you
don't judge your ancestors for what they
did um you kind of acknowledge it and go
you know i understand why you did what
you did i honor you for that but this is
the new pattern i'm going to be creating
that's true now let's circle back around
to the the body side of things
sure
just as much so you're working on the
mindset
sometimes
the
when people feel like they're they're
powerless in a certain situation or
they're struggling to set boundaries
or they're feeling anxiety how much of
that comes through just in
what they're feeding their body even
especially like if they're having a lot
of sugar
uh
snacking like
just just carbohydrates or
spiking their blood sugar or whatever
that is anything else that you want to
share on that oh yeah i mean 100 so if
we take anything trauma related you know
from the conversation there's a whole
other layer that is just strictly what
you're feeding your body which is why
it's so important so
you know if if you are um like you said
feeding yourself carbohydrates all day
long you know just because it's fast
it's easy it tastes good you're going to
be on a blood sugar roller coaster all
day you're going to be one of those
people that ex you know that experiences
hanger you know when you're angry and
you know hungry and angry
it's going to happen at regular
intervals because your blood sugar is
going up and down and crashing um and
then what ends up happening is it ends
up like a runaway train by the end of
the day it's like okay well i started my
day with like half a bagel well the end
of the day i need ice cream and cookies
and now i need something salty and you
know and and it just becomes this you
know horrible uh you know sort of like
snowball effect that accumulates by the
end of the day
and um
it can feel hard to get out of that
cycle because then what happens is
because you've eaten so much at the end
of the day you wake up in the morning
you don't want to eat or you eat like a
half a bagel because you heard breakfast
was good for you or whatever you start
the cycle all over again and you know
when your your food is not anchored by a
protein ideally into fiber everything
can get all you know wacky out of
control i mean we really did society a
major disservice by
releasing the food pyramid nine to
twelve servings of greens on the bottom
you know um you know i have a lot of
theories on that but let's just let's
just give everyone the benefit the doubt
and say that that was created because
people were more active at that time
we're not now we're just not so that 9
to 12 servings of grains not really a
great idea for most people
and you know not only from a blood sugar
management standpoint we're also looking
at how it's impacting the gut so
a lot of our neurotransmitters are
manufactured in the gut so if you're
feeding um you know some bad gut
bacteria some sugar those guys are going
to you know throw a wild party and
proliferate next you know and they're
gonna like more sugar and then your
cravings can come from the inside out
and you can feel like you have no
control and i have personal experience
with this so um yeah i was a few years
out of college and i was you know living
on my own
and of course i had gotten the bad habit
while i was in college of eating gummy
candy occasionally at night because i
was running track i was working out
twice a day at the time i needed it it
was a terrible food source but i needed
it so
graduate whatever i kid you not i woke
up at two in the morning and i had to
drive to the grocery store and get bulk
candy because i was craving it so bad
because the cravings were coming from my
gut they weren't coming from wow
psychological and then of course my car
broke down in the parking lot and i had
to call uh 9-1-1 and of course the cop
that showed up to rescue me i knew and
he's like what are you doing here and i
was too embarrassed to tell him why i
was there i said i needed medication or
something like that but you know
it was terrible but that's how real
gut cravings are and of course you know
this was right around the time i started
working with that naturopath and lo and
behold i had a candida overgrowth and
you know candida can cause crazy
sugar cravings that make you want to eat
anything not nailed down like in my case
right so you know it's food choices are
really important especially making sure
your guts balanced and you know and so
on so i'll add to that a lot of people
experience a lot of guilt and shame with
feeling like they're not in control of
their food choices and some of it could
be an imbalance with what they're eating
but more often than not it's an
imbalance coming from the gut which is
driving a lot of these choices and then
people wonder why
they can't stick to anything long term
it's because their gut is is really in
charge and driving everything wow
that's that's
amazing i think a lot of people that are
listening to this especially if they're
they're dealing with anxiety and worry
and fear
in their life
i notice in my life you know last year
um i was eating a lot of sugar and i was
hiding it and i was i had this sugar
addiction like yeah but talked about
mentioned to some people and as soon as
i like
stopped eating a lot of sugar
and
just started adding
leafy greens before every meal
not with a bunch of like dressing like i
literally just kind of eat the greens
by themselves
and having the fiber and then you know
supporting my adrenals
and and exercising
not a whole lot but just a little bit
every day
that alone has radically transformed my
life my business our income has gone up
my focus my ability to communicate has
gotten better my capacity to work with
people uh i stopped drinking alcohol as
well like
just all of that
has changed my life as a coach and it's
just some of the basic stuff that i've
learned
from people like yourself and
and
have started to apply to my life that i
see
that i just i really want like i've had
a number of people on here that aren't
nutritionists and
health coaches share the same thing that
you're sharing and so for those that are
listening right now maybe you've heard a
few of these same messages
um really take a look at how you're
eating if you're struggling to build
your business
absolutely if you're struggling to
actually build your business i'm not
talking about starving yourself to like
for the focus of losing weight like
that's not what i'm talking about and i
notice a lot of people especially women
as they get into coaching they think oh
i can't show up on camera unless i'm a
certain weight
you'll feel more confident by
just
eating what supports your body
and and and it the scale isn't the focus
but it's like how can i make my brain
work better
how can i feel better about myself
and
you know there's a lot of messaging that
goes on especially
i have a lot of clients that are over
the age of 40 and 50 years old there's
been a lot of messaging around
self-worth
and the body
that i think
our current generation has swung the
opposite direction
um
speak to that a little bit like
self-worth and and just loving yourself
where you're at and who you are but also
taking care of yourself and how it's an
act of self-love to actually take care
of yourself oh my gosh that's like such
a great topic um
so okay so so the first thing is yes
it's it's very important to love
yourself where you're at
and you know if you're someone that's
you know in the process of trying to get
your body back to a more comfortable
place buy clothes that feel good on you
you know buy clothes that look good on
you um don't stress out when you get
dressed because i know for a lot of
women it can be like a panic moment when
you try to put on a pair of pants that
don't actually fit you know and i think
the easiest thing to do is
run to the scale see how bad it is which
never works by the way and then you know
suddenly commit yourself to this crash
diet that never works and then the cycle
repeats itself you know and and the
people think that they're doing it out
of self-love but really they're doing
out of panic and reactionary mode where
it's like
oh no i'm you know
what happened so the first thing i would
say is to not engage in any behaviors
that are going to bring guilt and shame
on you because any time you do that
that's a surefire way to know that your
approach is going to fail so if your
approach involves weighing yourself all
the time i would not do that i have some
clients that don't weigh in we don't
weigh in at all we just go based on how
you feel how your clothes fit you know
things like that i have other clients
that weigh in every 30 days because they
don't want to put themselves in that
position where they need to see a change
every day or every week because the
skill is really not the greatest gauge
of progress anyway i mean
um i have a really great before and
after picture of a lady and in her
before she's 182 pounds and she has what
looks like a beach ball size midsection
you know uh eight months after the the
process she's still 192 pounds but she
has an hourglass figure well what
happened
she re she did something called body
recomposition where she lost body fat
she fixed her gut i'm assuming this
wasn't my client this was somebody i
found online
and she built some muscle and lost fat
so you know if your only gauge is the
scale you're doing yourself a huge
disservice because there could be many
changes going on so it's important to
love yourself where you're at and just
understand that it's part of a process
you should really unfriend anybody on
facebook that you know or or any social
media platform that makes you feel badly
about yourself and that goes for
body
business anything i have gone through
this you know see this mad season of
unfriending people right and left that i
know has smoke and mirrors messaging
because it's really toxic
and it's
misrepresentation
so there's that so
very important to love and accept
yourself and instead of focusing on what
you can take away from your body focus
on what you can give it instead that's
super important now the other part that
i want to add to that is that i feel
that the
beauty at any size movement has been
grossly misrepresented so what i mean by
that is that the concept of there being
beauty at any size yes we're not all the
same size however what has kind of
spiraled out of control is that people
are now assuming that
very unhealthy body compositions is okay
and you should ignore certain signs and
symptoms right and
you know
you see where it became a very gray area
so i just want to caution people about
that i think that it's wonderful if it's
helped women accept themselves that
haven't been able to absolutely up until
this point i really do
um but we don't need self-hatred at all
no
but the the one can
the one
filter i guess i would add to that is
just make sure in that process are you
ignoring signs and symptoms are you
healthy are you taking care of yourself
are you cutting years off of your life
yes because of
certain things that you're doing i mean
i even take account of that
all the time myself i think it's so
important
absolutely absolutely i mean like for
example
um i was just talking to someone the
other day and they had mentioned that
they um
so they had a belt that had gone up a
significant amount of sizes and that was
actually indicative of a gut problem but
at the time they said
beauty at any size i'm just going to
accept myself for this
you know and they were in an unhealthy
weight to begin with and in retrospect
now that years have gone by and the gut
issues compounded they said i really
wish i would have paid closer attention
to when my belt sizes started to
suddenly go up for no reason turns out
they had massive bacterial gut
overgrowth yeah so you know i mean it's
not to say that anyway
you know what i mean
our bodies aren't going to stay the same
size all the time but
in situations like that
the messaging from the beauty of any
size movement really kind of
uh
negated some of the signals her body was
trying to give her of hey there's
something here it's just as toxic as
you know basically telling people like
that it's okay it'd be like
having a car that is like making a whole
bunch of really loud noises and driving
it on the road and
and then you know well i'm just going to
accept this car that it's going to break
down and it's going to stop working yeah
um it'll grow back
and in fact some of that messaging i
could see being perpetuated by big
pharma
oh no doubt being perpetuated by
uh people that benefit from people being
sick
absolutely
you got to be aware of how that
messaging is monetized
absolutely again
we're not talking about self
hate like hating yourself for what your
body is
but it's like there's sometimes there's
symptoms and it's like okay
maybe something's off here let's take a
look at what that is and and what are
some things that like people could start
doing
you know they're like well i
i can't afford to work with a
functional medicine person which i think
anybody could find the budget for it if
they
really looked but what are some things
that they could start with at least
like
to do
that would start to at least put them in
in a more positive direction
yeah absolutely and one thing i'll say
you know whether people are interested
in working with me or somebody else that
does what i do typically people like me
will have multiple tiers of affordable
access to people yeah to programs and
things like that which is what i have
and i think there are a lot of other
functional professionals like me that
have the same thing so that you can get
access to health no matter your budget
so i do have something available like
that where you could you know invest as
low as 20 a month and get help all the
way up to
vip one-on-one coaching so i do want to
point that out to people that i've had a
lot of people not even reach out to me
for help because they assumed they
couldn't afford me and i
you know i'm thinking oh no i've
actually created very affordable things
for people of all budgetary you know i
know you have you know like you like you
and i have worked on together um so i
just want to point that out to people
too um seek out people have different
tiers of service so that you can get
access no matter what you can afford
um but if you wanted to try some things
on your own i would say
um
just try something very simple i would
say that the two things that can make
the greatest impact your overall day
is
how you set up your breakfast and lunch
so the way those two meals are set up
will completely dictate what you do at
the end of the day so i'm gonna throw a
little reversal in here that'll probably
throw some people off but breakfast is
not the most important meal the day
lunch actually is because your digestive
strength is the greatest at lunch time
so
at lunch time and it's it's it's really
sad because we've been taught to you
know pack a really dry salad and throw
some sad grilled chicken on there and
maybe some balsamic vinaigrette
and our little salads like the size of a
cereal bowl and we're like okay i had a
healthy lunch and then you're starving
an hour later so you want to toss out
that whole idea that you've been taught
instead
make
the biggest
you know possible salad that you can
think of i eat mine out of a mixing bowl
because it's so big um a lot of people
do actually and you know add your
chicken and then add all of your
favorite types of veggies you know
carrots peppers whatever throw in some
nuts you know maybe throw in some
berries some tahini something like that
make it really big because your lunch is
really going to anchor your choices for
the rest of the day and the beauty of
that is that you don't even have to make
it yourself if you're a busy
entrepreneur
or you know wife mom dad you know boss
whatever you can order that out no
problem i mean one of my favorite things
to say to people all the time is this
when they say they don't have time i go
all right well you're gonna have to eat
at some point right and they're like
yeah and i'm like then make the best
choice you can you know you're not just
going to stop eating just make a
different choice
so
make sure you anchor your lunch with a
big old portion of protein
big portion of veggies that can be
dinner leftovers you have to make it
hard
and then the breakfast the same thing
make sure you choose a protein you
choose a veggie or some type of fiber so
you know you could do like scrambled
eggs and veggies and poultry sausage
that's fine you know and most people can
do something like that or i'll have
people do like a protein shake with a
handful of leafy greens and you know a
spoonful of almond or almond or some
type of nut butter those two things are
going to go so far in your journey that
you will be like light years ahead by
the time you reach out to somebody like
me or
you know or me whatever for help that
you have already done some of the
legwork and a practitioner would then be
like great you've done the hard stuff
let's take you to the next level now so
that's what i would really recommend and
that would be true of you know
um of trying to reach out to any
practitioner do as much legwork as you
can first if you're capable and then
reach out to that person for help
because then they're going to be able to
take you like light years ahead of where
you took yourself yeah
that's amazing and and
where can people find info about working
with you
um you just go visit
www.livehealthywithbecky
and it's becky with an i
not a y dot com
awesome i am right here on your website
this is great i just love all the
different stuff plus you have the
supplements that you can help people
with
you really have become like a one-stop
shop you got your insider circle
coaching your your weekly fat loss your
one-on-one coaching
this is amazing this is really just
incredible how you're helping people and
i'm so thankful that you were able to to
be here today to just bring some of your
knowledge and some of your wisdom to
everybody
well i i appreciate it and i appreciate
the opportunity you know that you gave
me to come and speak and i mean we've
done great work together over the years
too you've really helped me streamline a
lot of things that i offer and you know
make sure that it's a really great suite
of services that can you know anybody
can can access no matter what their
budget is
very awesome
well everybody listen check out
becky over at livehealthywithbecky.com
we'll put the link here on the post and
if you're somebody that is again
struggling with some of these issues or
maybe you know somebody that is you're a
coach your trainer you're in
corporate you're just wanting to
to have a a more fulfilled life i think
that's really what it is it's like you
want more of what you want you can get
more of what you want by taking care of
your mindset and your body
share this episode with somebody
uh and and and and help them out and say
like you know this is this is
something that i think might be a good
starting place for you i think really
this this episode is a good starting
place for a lot of people to explore
um the ideas of why they do what they do
and some small changes they they can
make both mentally
and physically
to to accomplish their goals better any
any final thoughts or encouragement that
you want to share with anybody sure
so i will say
to encourage people those of you that
are you know scared to embark on
anything you know any changes or
anything like that
one thing that's helpful to know and
this might be a helpful motivator is how
you show up in private is how you show
up in public
so if you want to if you have big dreams
of you know taking your business to the
next level how you treat your body in
private you know and your healthy habits
and so on it's magnified through your
business
and there's this this unspoken you know
kind of energy shift that people pick up
on with you and they're like oh i just i
just really want to work with this
person and it's because you're taking
such great care of yourself behind the
scenes so it's worth it so don't let the
process intimidate you just pick small
things that you want to tackle um please
don't do anything crazy like downloading
a three-day juice cleanse or anything
like that because it it's not going to
give you the long-term result that
you're looking for it's just going to
drive you into more panic guilt and
shame once it's over so
really focus on those sustainable
lifelong habits make sure it's something
your whole family can do you can do it
all together yeah and um just enjoy the
process don't be so hard on yourself
yeah i i've noticed everybody at least
that i've worked with or that i'm
connected with that does a lot in the
health and fitness that's their same
messages yeah to embrace the process
um you know
do what you can do be aware
but like love yourself through the whole
thing
take care of your mental health as well
as your physical
years back i had studied a lot about
health and fitness and nutrition
just to like go after like a
bodybuilding type goal oh yeah i
completely neglected the mindset side of
it and swung right back worse than i was
before
afterwards i had the six pack and i had
like
lost all this weight and and i was i
think i was like seven percent body fat
i was like the first time in my whole
life
i did a photo shoot and all this and
then immediately ended up gaining it all
all back
and actually hating the gym and hating
working out and hating eating because i
didn't work on what was up here
and so i've spent the last four years
really dialing this in more than
anything else and now i'm starting to
add in the fitness and the eating and
all of that piece by piece and i'm
noticing
that it's sustainable that way that that
i think we can't separate the mind from
the body mind and body go
together yes absolutely i mean and i i
appreciate you sharing that you know and
and you know being transparent about it
because i think that's a lot of people's
experience i mean
i came from an industry where i dieted
for figure shows i did it twice actually
yeah and it's a very extreme process and
i really think it was divine
intervention because each time i would
get a certain number of weeks out from
the stage i would have some sort of
really debilitating injury wow
degree where i ended up in physical
therapy i mean at one point i had uh
worn down cartilage in my knees and you
know all these other issues i couldn't
even climb the stairs and i was trying
to work a corporate job and i was like
i cannot do this this is a for fun hobby
you know i i can't sacrifice my my job
stability for for something like this
and what you're describing after you do
something extreme like that it's really
real you feel lost you don't know what
to do in many cases the pendulum swings
in the other direction you extremes i
mean and to a degree i wonder if the
amygdala in the brain has been triggered
you know that fear response because that
will drive you know what's going on and
create these aversions to the things
that cause such a traumatic experience
the first time around
so i love that you shared that because i
think a lot of people think like i just
need to go to a boot camp and have
somebody whip me into shape i need
something that's like super strict and
it's like well just be careful because
whatever measure you use to take it off
is the measure you're going to have to
use to maintain it wow
that's a that's actually a
very biblical statement
right um
i i i have heard that
any sort of like growth in your life in
your business that you do without god
you're gonna have to sustain it without
him too and we can't
and i'm like like that applies even in
so many different avenues is like if
you're using
certain tools like
guilt and shame to drive you which is
what for me my shame is what drove me
yeah
my i i literally
had hatred towards my body that drove me
to change it
interesting and and that was the only
motivator i had and as soon as i got to
a certain place and i loved how it
looked i had no motivation
yeah and i bet that's a lot a lot of
people deal with that even in their
businesses even and and i'll just be
super transparent i try to be as
transparent as possible
all the time
i've even noticed some of that can come
up in business
a
shame and guilt of not having a certain
level of income drives me to increase my
income and then it comes right back down
and so having to learn to have
a the self discipline to do it
without those motivators be to change my
reason why i'm doing this
and and then see setting up myself with
systems for success to where i don't
burn myself out
and so that it's it's enjoyable and it's
fun and the fun is back into it that the
fun isn't because i
accomplished something that the fun
isn't because i'm accomplishing
something the fun is just in being
who god made me to be
absolutely from that place and i think
that's so powerful for people when it
comes to your body your mind your
business
all of that well this has been great i
think i might have to have you
back on here
again to talk even more about this i
feel like we could talk for like another
hour oh absolutely i have plenty other
areas that we could talk about yeah we
could talk about big pharma we could
talk about quantum spirituality we could
talk about totally ancestral traumas i
do a lot of these things and i'll just
i'll close with this so there's a ceo
that i've been working with she's a ceo
of a big very very big company and she
developed type 2 diabetes out of nowhere
but then also type 1 diabetes out of
nowhere so then what is she the doctors
said well i guess she's type 1 and a
half where she's both insulin dependent
but because she's not manufacturing her
own but she also can't control her blood
sugar so she was on drugs for both
and she was working with a mutual friend
and mutual friend said you really need
to talk to becky about this so we get in
touch
and in let me tell you in eight months
of working together now we've done no
dietary modifications let me just point
this out only doing mindset work she has
gotten off of her type 1 diabetes
medication she shed most of her type 2
diabetes medication except for a little
bit of metformin and that is just from
doing mindset
wow that's it mindsetting
amazing
so that's how important it is
a lot of people like
don't think that the mind and mindset we
talk a lot about mindset on this podcast
i would say that it's about 66 percent
of what i talk about and then strategy
is probably about the other 33 percent
yeah is because
and and i'm a testament to this i had
all the strategies for the coaching
business
and the course business but my income
has gone up like crazy this past year
because of the mindset peaks absolutely
because i'm finally
i have
up here in order and how it's coming out
is flowing from that place and i'm still
working on what's up here i i'm telling
you i
i
am going through something right now i'm
not ready to like talk about with
everybody
but on the other side of it i know i'm
gonna i'm gonna share it just some some
stuff i'm gonna be talking to my
therapist about this week that really
um we have our we have our family here
this week like my wife's whole family's
here and it triggered something in me
that i didn't know was there that now
i'm like okay
this is an area that i i actually it was
just amplified but it's been under the
surface
for the last year that i need to work on
and so when we can look at even our
triggers i actually start to get excited
if i get super triggered about something
and it's a new trigger
that's more amplified i'm like okay
i can go to work on that and the rest of
my life is going to change
absolutely oh that is i love that
because that is so true once you get to
a certain point in the process you look
for those triggers and when something
triggers you it's like you said it's
like this is great i can't wait to
discuss
you know instead of beating yourself up
about it and being mad like oh i got
another trigger again
kind of like in your body even if you're
like oh i'm okay i'm struggling i
reached a plateau instead of getting
frustrated with the plateau
reframing it with excitement of okay
what can i learn from this what what
what can i
go back into and learn and so i think
even just in our lives in our businesses
anywhere where we feel stuck or
something that's sticking us is
reframing that
is reframing i've been i've been
teaching people um
i need to get the exact language but
basically it's it's what tony robbins
teaches about pain versus pleasure and
reassociating what was painful and that
like you hated yourself about and you
didn't like as a pleasurable experience
and that they're actually the same
feeling inside of you but there's a
different story you tell about it and so
oftentimes when i'm nervous to
talk with somebody in a sales call or
i'm nervous to go into a situation i
reframe it now as excitement because
there's a lesson for me by pressing
through that and it allows me to break
past my fear reassociating my fears with
that now this is this is how again a lot
of people there's some negatives to this
how they can get into abusive
relationships because they end up
associating the abuse with love because
that's the only way they can cope this
is how extreme sports people they
associate they get addicted to that
adrenaline rush right stuff like that so
we got to be aware of what's healthy
what's not
um but but in the process of building
your business your health journey your
mindset journey you're gonna come up to
places where you're stuck
where it's gonna you're gonna get afraid
and you're gonna almost feel like
i can't go on
and that's where if we can reframe that
as this is actually an exciting moment
for me that i'm feeling this
yes that can change people's lives and
if i could just help more people
understand that i'm starting to talk
more about it
like when you feel the most fear
that's when you lean in
that's when you get excited yes and
reframing your fear as excitement when
it comes to your business
right absolutely because in business
we're not really putting ourselves into
life or death
situations um
even i
one of the scariest things when people
have to spend money on advertising or
spend money to build their
landing pages or their sales copy or to
get coaching right
but
that might be a temporary
fear of is it going to produce a result
but by leaning into that you're going to
learn a whole lot that you would not
have learned by not doing that i love it
yep my favorite phrase is i win either
way
yup i win either way you know and in the
other way like i love what you said
because like you know guilt and shame
and anger if people are using that to
drive them that's a finite resource it's
going to run out
you know and and it's like you said it's
it's very biblical you know what you use
to build your business just like your
body you know whatever if you're doing
it apart from from god and you're trying
to use artificial motivators
it just leads to destruction no matter
what we're talking about whether it's
the body you end up with you know
breakdown on the cellular level you know
um
or in your business your business
crumbles because you've built it out of
vengeance i i've seen plenty of people
you know unfortunately have that type of
experience or they they build it out of
whatever the
the the the so-called inadequacy that
they feel that they have yeah to prove
themselves exactly
proving yourself can only it can
motivate you to get started but it's not
going to sustain you right
and so you gotta find something else to
keep going forward and that's why
usually a lot of people prove themselves
and they drop back where they are then
they gotta prove themselves again and
and i i i actually know a guy right now
he's been on that cycle for 20 years
and he's made millions
and then always loses it makes millions
and loses it
and
and one of his biggest fears is being
wrong
wow
one of his biggest fears is people
calling him out on being wrong as well
very interesting and so like internally
it's this this idea of and i was
actually talking with a close friend of
mine that we both know him and it's like
you can it's it's clear as day from
everybody on the outside
yeah this pattern but he
has this deep need to be right all the
time
yeah that is preventing him from even
seeing it wow that's where i think a lot
of people get stuck on this need to be
right and to do the right thing
yep
and to never be wrong it's and it comes
from insecurity it comes from fear of
yeah
if we just lay that down that's why i
tell people
you're gonna make mistakes you're gonna
make messes you're going to be wrong
sometimes that's okay yeah that's part
of the process you're gonna mess up
and you can learn from it so that then
you go
and win in the future
exactly you win either way and you know
a lesson is usually permitted to repeat
in your life until you learn it so in
some cases it goes on for 20 years you
know like in that
particular man's case that you mentioned
so the faster you can learn it the
better but you know
i i really love your your explanation
with tony robbins because it's you have
a choice you know and
i tell my clients that listen you win
either way even if you don't achieve
your result you're gonna learn really
intimately what did not work for you and
usually it's something extreme
yeah
this is great this has been such a good
episode thank you for being here again
sure everybody check out
livehealthywithbecky.com
and share the episode with people if
you're a coach or trainer hop on one of
the upcoming live events that i'm doing
grow your life everybody and we'll talk
soon